All right, final section of this chapter, wound healing.
The idea here, and the reason why I sort of placed this
at the very end of this chapter,
is that we've been talking about inflammation,
but we should remember that any time we have inflammation,
as soon as inflammation begins,
we also initiate a process called healing.
And the idea here is that inflammation is a destructive process.
It damages tissues.
And any time we damage tissues,
we're going to want to heal those tissues.
And so healing is a consequence or a subsequent consequence of inflammation.
Now, it's important to note that healing actually occurs via two processes.
It's usually a combination of both.
Regeneration, which refers to healing so that we actually replace the damaged tissue
with the tissue itself by regenerating it, or repair.
And the idea with repair is that instead of replacing the tissue with itself,
we replace the tissue with a scar, all right, with collagen and fibrosis.
And so usually when we have healing,
it occurs by a combination of both regeneration and repair.
Now, again, as I've stated, what is regeneration?
It's replacement of the damaged tissue with the native tissue.
And, I mean, that would be the ideal.
Anytime you have damage, you would obviously prefer to replace it with native tissue.
But we can't always do that.
And regeneration, it's important to note that it's dependent on the regenerative capacity of the tissue.
So this then leads to a classic examiner's type of topic that you should be familiar with,
which is that tissues can be divided into three types based on their regenerative capacity.
So the first type of tissue are called labile tissues.
What are labile tissues?
These are tissues that are constantly cycling.
Basically, the tissue has stem cells, and the stem cells are constantly regenerating the tissue,
just as part of our normal physiology.
For example, our bowel is constantly regenerating.
The skin is constantly regenerating.
The red blood cells, the white blood cells, the platelets are constantly regenerating.
So these are examples of labile tissues,
and they have the ability to regenerate tissue when they're damaged.
So, for example, let's just take the skin.
If you were to get a paper cut and you were to look for the paper cut two years later,
you wouldn't be able to find it.
In fact, you wouldn't be able to find it a couple days later.
You wouldn't even remember it a week later.
And that's because you basically knock out the superficial layer of the epithelium,
but you have stem cells, which are called basal cells,
which have the ability to regenerate the tissue completely.
And so you'll get regeneration of the tissue.
Same thing with the small and large bowel.
When a patient gets diarrhea, you don't need to, you know,
gets an infection in the GI tract and gets diarrhea.
You don't worry about transplanting the bowel or something like that
because the bowel basically has the ability to regenerate itself.
So that's the first type of tissue.
And here we can get into a little bit of histology,
and the examiners like to,
by reminding ourselves where the stem cells are actually located.
So, for example, if I asked you where are the stem cells in the small and large bowel,
the answer would be in the crypts.
You need to know that.
If I asked you where are the stem cells in the skin,
the answer would be in the basal layer,
which is the very lowest layer, the most inner layer of the epidermis.
You need to know that.
What's the stem cell of the bone marrow?
The hematopoietic stem cell.
Now, we can't see the hematopoietic stem cell on histology,
but do you know the marker of the hematopoietic stem cell,
which is very high yield, shows up on exams all the time,
used in clinics when you do transplants?
Do you know it?
Okay, CD34.
You've got to know that.
Bone marrow stem cells are CD34 positive.
You will use this in clinics,
especially when you do autologous stem cell transplanting,
and you need to know this for examinations as well.
Not listed here, but I could ask you another question.
What's the stem cell of the lung, of the alveoli of the lung?
Excellent.
Type 2 pneumocytes.
You need to know that.
The type 2 pneumocyte is the stem cell of the lung.
We'll talk about type 2 pneumocytes
when we do the lung lecture, however.
Anyway, that's labile tissues.
I put this picture in here to remind you
where the stem cells are in the bowel
because they ask it on exams.
And so these are the crypts down here,
way at the bottom of these regions like this.
This is the crypt.
And the stem cells basically sit at the very base of the crypts.
That's where the stem cells of the bowel are located.
Here's a picture of the skin.
This is the epidermis.
This is the dermis.
And you know that the epidermis consists of keratinocytes,
and there's this dark layer here
that you can kind of see running along the base,
and that is the basal layer.
I'm going to erase this so that you can now see
that this little dark blue layer,
this represents the basal layer.
And the basal layer is the regenerative stem cell layer of the skin.
All right, stable tissues.
What are stable tissues?
These are tissues that are quiescent.
They're stable.
They sort of sit outside of cell cycle.
But they have the ability to reenter cell cycle.
And this is the second type of tissue present in the body.
The classic example of this would be the liver,
so that if you actually partially resect the liver,
you can get regeneration of the liver,
and that occurs by compensatory hyperplasia.
So what happens is when there's partial resection of the liver,
each of the hepatocytes present within the liver
has the ability to come out of quiescence
and to reenter cell cycle.
And when it reenters the cell cycle,
it can divide and allow for regeneration of the liver.
And so this is a very high-yield example of a stable tissue,
which is the liver.
Another example of a stable tissue
is the proximal renal tubule of the kidney.
Remember that when patients undergo a tubular necrosis,
ATN, they get destruction of the proximal renal tubular cells,
and those cells can regenerate,
but it takes some time because those are stable cells.
And so often we have to place patients,
well, it's not often, but it occurs on occasion,
where you might have to place a patient
who has ATN, severe ATN, on dialysis
to support them until the kidney
actually regenerates the proximal renal tubule.
And that's another example of a stable tissue.
So again, these are some sort of classic examples
of stable tissue.
The third type of tissue in the human body
is called permanent tissue.
And it's called permanent because it is permanent.
It lacks significant regenerative potential.
And there are three key tissues in the human body
that lack significant regenerative potential
include the myocardium, the skeletal muscle,
and the neurons.
These tissues don't technically have
significant amounts of stem cells.
And therefore, why don't I say these tissues
don't classically have significant amount
of stem cell capability.
And therefore, once they get damaged,
they're not able to regenerate themselves.
And so what's the classic occurrence
if these tissues get damaged?
The classic way by which they would heal
is called repair.
And remember, the idea in repair
is that you can't give back the normal tissue.
So instead, you have to replace that damage
with a fibrous scar.
So when will this occur?
It will occur when a tissue lacks regenerative capacity.
For example, when you get a myocardial infarction
in the heart,
when you get a myocardial infarction in the heart,
the mechanism of healing is always a fibrous scar.
The end result of myocardial infarction
is always a fibrous scar.
Why?
Because the heart does not have the ability
to regenerate tissue.
So this would be a classic picture
that can show up on an examination.
And you can clearly see that this is the heart.
This happens to be the ventricle.
And can you see that there is this white scar
indicating that there was a prior myocardial infarction?
And the reason why we get scarring in the heart,
again, is because the myocardium is a permanent tissue.
Now let me take you back and just remind you
that there is one more example
where you would get repair.
And that would be if the regenerative stem cells are lost.
For example, if you get a paper cut on the skin,
the skin will actually heal completely
and you won't be able to find the paper cut
a couple weeks later.
However, if you cut yourself with a steak knife,
let's just say for example,
you might go deep enough
that you actually take out a piece of skin
such that the basal cells are removed.
And if the basal cells are removed,
then you're going to get a scar
instead of a replacement with skin.
And that's why when you get a very deep cut,
you can actually see a scar form
and you could years later say,
oh, I remember this scar.
I got this when I was cutting steak, for example.
And that would be another example of repair.
And so that's why I've stated here
that it occurs when the regenerative stem cells are lost,
for example, with a deep cut to the skin,
or when the tissue lacks regenerative capacity,
for example, myocardial infarction.
All right, so both of those are kind of high yield.
Now, when repair is occurring,
repair means what?
It refers to the replacement of the tissue with scar.
The initial phase of repair
will be called granulation tissue.
That's the very initial phase of repair.
And what does granulation tissue consist of?
Fibroblasts, capillaries, and myofibroblasts.
There are three major components of granulation tissue.
Now, what do the capillaries do?
They provide nutrients.
What do the fibroblasts do?
They deposit type 3 collagen.
And what do the myofibroblasts do?
They contract the wound down.
Each of these are very important to be familiar with.
But let me take a step back.
First of all, when we talk about granulation tissue,
I want to make it very clear
that granulation tissue is different than a granuloma.
Unfortunately, sometimes students confuse these two terms
because they sound a little bit similar.
What is granuloma?
Granuloma is a subtype of chronic inflammation.
And what's the hallmark of granuloma?
Granuloma, epithelioid, histiocyte.
And how is a granuloma formed?
IL-12 from the macrophage hits the CD4-positive T cell,
converting it to a helper-type, TH1-type cell.
And the TH1 cell secretes interferon gamma
that gives the macrophage an epithelioid histiocyte appearance.
Okay?
And so granuloma is distinct from granulation tissue.
Granulation tissue is the initial phase of repair
when you're forming a scar.
Now, granulation tissue consists of fibroblasts,
and the fibroblasts deposit type 3 collagen.
It consists of capillaries,
and the capillaries provide the nutrients.
And then the granulation tissue also consists of myofibroblasts,
and these contract down the wound.
And I'll talk about this in a little bit more detail in a few slides,
but let's see a picture first, or let's look at a picture first.
So this is granulation tissue,
and you can see that this granulation tissue
is comprised of these blood vessels.
And in addition to these blood vessels,
you can clearly see that there's this deposition of collagen
and the presence of some of these fibroblasts,
which are also part of the granulation tissue.
So again, this is the classic histologic finding of granulation tissue.
Now, it's important to recall or remember or to learn
that eventually granulation tissue will produce a scar.
Okay, so that's the end result.
Like I said, granulation tissue is the early form
of what will eventually become a scar.
And one of the key features that distinguishes
granulation tissue from a scar
is that when you have a scar,
the type 3 collagen of the granulation tissue
is replaced with type 1 collagen.
Maybe this is a good point to take a step back
and just remind ourselves of collagen
and its different subtypes.
So I'm going to actually clear out the board here
and give you a whiteboard.
Can you remember a few important points of collagen number 1?
One important collagen is type 1 collagen.
And do you remember what type 1 collagen is seen in?
It's seen in bone.
And one of the ways that people remember that
is that when you think about bone,
it has the word 1 within it.
So that reminds you of type 1 collagen.
But what I'd like you to know is that
one of the key features of type 1 collagen
is its strength.
It has strong tensile strength.
It provides support and it has the tensile strength
that is particular to type 1 collagen.
Okay, type 2 collagen is predominantly seen in cartilage.
And one of the ways by which people remember that
is cartilage.
So some people say cartilage, type 2 collagen.
Type 3 collagen, if I had to summarize it,
the way I remember it,
is that type 3 collagen is sort of classic for its pliability.
It's pliable.
And so where do we see type 3 collagen?
Blood vessels, which need the ability to stretch.
We see type 3 collagen in granulation tissue
because granulation tissue is sort of the initial phase of scar.
It needs to be able to stretch and mold into a final scar.
And we see it in embryonic tissue.
There's a lot of type 3 collagen in embryonic skin, for example,
because the baby's growing and needs to be able to stretch.
So if I had to summarize type 3 collagen,
I would summarize it with the word pliability.
And then type 4 collagen is predominantly seen in basement membrane.
So these are some high yields concerning collagen.
I just wanted to give you that.
But I want to take you back and remind you
that granulation tissue has type 3 collagen initially, right?
And that's produced by the fibroblasts.
And the type 3 collagen is important because it's pliable.
But eventually, you want to replace it with type 1 collagen.
And you want type 1 collagen because that really provides the stability necessary in the final scar.
Important to know in high yield for examinations is that when we want to get rid of the type 3 collagen
and eventually convert it to type 1 collagen, we're going to use collagenase,
which is going to eat up that type 3 collagen.
And very high yield, zinc, is a cofactor for collagenase in order to remove type 3 collagen
and replace it with type 1, okay?
So that's in biochemistry.
And you'll see we're going to hit on that one more time before we end this lecture.
What is the mechanism of regeneration and repair?
Well, the mechanism of regeneration and repair is that it is mediated by paracrine signaling
by growth factors.
All right, and it's an interaction of these factors with receptors that results in growth.
And all I'm trying to really highlight here is that there are factors.
The factors are secreted, for example, by macrophages.
And the factors will then bind receptors.
And it's these receptor-factor interactions that will result in regeneration and repair.
That's what I'm trying to highlight.
And the reason I'm even bringing up this discussion is because examiners like to go after
different subtypes of molecules that are important for the process.
For example, TGF-alpha is an important epithelial and fibroblast growth factor.
All right, TGF-beta is an important fibroblast growth factor, and it inhibits inflammation.
But this should not be so hard for you to remember because if you go back to one of our earlier
lectures when we talked about acute inflammation and macrophages, remember that I said that macrophages,
if they come in and they see that there is no longer a need for inflammation, they'll sort
of shut down inflammation and turn on the healing response.
And they said there's two major molecules you should be familiar with, IL-10 and TGF-beta.
Well, here is exactly that same TGF-beta.
So what is TGF-beta going to do?
It's going to cause fibroblast growth, which is important for healing, and it's going to
inhibit inflammation to shut down that inflammatory process.
Another important example would be platelet-derived growth factor.
Now, again, no rocket science.
What do platelets do?
Platelets help to seal a blood vessel that's been damaged, correct?
So if platelets are activated, one of the important things that they release is platelet-derived
growth factor.
And what is that growth factor going to do?
Well, it's going to help the endothelium regrow.
It's going to help the smooth muscle of the blood vessel wall regrow.
And it's going to help fibroblasts come in for the healing.
And so that's platelet-derived growth factor.
Here's one that's very important to be aware of, fibroblast growth factor.
And I would say it's very important because although it's called fibroblast growth factor,
it actually is a very strong angiogenic factor.
Angiogenic helps to grow blood vessels.
And so it's important to know this one because it sort of is different than the rest in the
sense that name doesn't necessarily indicate what it does.
It's also important for skeletal development, but we'll talk about that in your musculoskeletal
lectures.
And finally, vascular endothelial growth factor, vascular endothelial growth factor, obviously,
is going to be important for angiogenesis.
Now, when we have cutaneous healing, that is healing of the skin, there are two ways by
which that can occur.
Primary intention, which is what?
We take the wound edges.
For example, you get a big cut.
You go to the ER, and they take the wound edges, and they use suture to bring them together.
Now, why would you want to bring the two edges together?
Because that will result in minimal scar formation, right?
Because the skin has the ability to heal, and it'll fill in the defect.
Another way by which we can get cutaneous healing is called secondary intention.
And what's secondary intention?
Basically, we don't let the edges be approximated, so we don't stitch them together.
Instead, the tissue remains open, and granulation tissue fills in the defect.
Now, when granulation tissue fills in the defect, what's going to happen?
You're going to get a big scar.
But more importantly, at least for examinations, is that the granulation tissue will cause contraction
of that wound slightly, all right?
So there could be a potential examination question where they ask you that a patient has a large
wound that is healed by secondary intention, and six weeks later, you notice that the wound
has significantly reduced in size.
And then they can ask you, what's the mechanism by which this wound actually reduces in size?
And the answer is the myofibroblast.
Now, let's go back.
Remember that granulation tissue has three components.
It has capillaries, it has fibroblasts that lay down type 3 collagen, and then it has
myofibroblasts.
And the myo means that they have some contractile function.
So the myofibroblasts have the ability to contract the wound and make it smaller.
And that's actually high yield for examination.
So that's why I actually brought this topic up to begin with.
Delayed wound healing.
What is delayed wound healing?
This is where a patient has a wound, but it doesn't heal in the appropriate time.
Infection is the most common cause.
If there is infection, there'll be chronic inflammation, or there'll be continued inflammation,
and the continued inflammation will then impair the healing of the wound.
So that's the most common cause of delayed wound healing.
Another cause would be vitamin C deficiency.
Why do we need vitamin C?
Well, let's go back.
Remind ourselves, when collagen is produced by the cell, it is produced as separate alpha
chains.
The alpha chains wrap around each other, and the final result of the alpha chains wrapping
around each other is something called procollagen.
Now, procollagen will eventually then be secreted outside of the cell, and it will be cross-linked
outside of the cell.
In order to cross-link the procollagen, one of the things that has to occur before cross-linking
can occur is that you need to hydroxylate the proline and lysine residues of procollagen.
This is getting a little complex, so maybe let me just remind you that when you have collagen,
collagen's normal amino acid structure is glycine, and then XY.
It's called GlyXY.
So glycine is usually one amino acid, and then the next amino acid is usually, this X
refers to proline or lysine, but usually proline.
And then this Y is usually going to be proline or lysine, and that proline or lysine will actually
get hydroxylated, so that it'll get an OH group added to it.
Now, how does that OH group get added?
Well, vitamin C is necessary to add that OH group to create hydroxyproline or hydroxylysine.
Now, why do you want that OH group?
Because this OH group in the sequence of collagen is necessary so that when you want to cross-link
another collagen molecule, it's cross-linking occurs via the OH groups, and that then allows
procollagen to be strengthened to the final collagen molecule.
And so vitamin C is a necessary chemical, or we can say a necessary vitamin, for the strengthening
of collagen.
So that should be clear now.
And that's why I say that vitamin C can result in delayed wound healing.
Another important molecule that could result in delayed wound healing is lack of copper.
If there's a copper deficiency, there can be delayed wound healing, and that's because
the enzyme that cross-links lysine and hydroxylysine to form that stable collagen, one of the enzymes
is called lysol oxidase, and lysol oxidase requires copper as a cofactor.
So if there's a lack of copper, we won't be able to cross-link our collagen, and that would
give us delayed wound healing.
And the final deficiency that could result in delayed wound healing is zinc.
Why do we need zinc?
We've already talked about it.
Well, remember that granulation tissue normally contains type 3 collagen, and we need to convert
that type 3 collagen to type 1 collagen to give the final strength of the scar.
But we need zinc in order to be able to properly do that, because the collagenase that removes
type 1 collagen actually requires zinc as a cofactor.
So that's that.
And these are all high yield, because they all tie into biochemistry.
Now other causes of delayed wound healing include foreign body, because that would induce
chronic inflammation.
Ischemia, because you're not going to get good blood supply to the tissue, so that would
then decrease the ability to heal the tissue.
Diabetes is associated with delayed wound healing.
And malnutrition.
Again, if there's not good nutrition, there's not going to be the necessary building blocks
to allow wound healing to occur.
Dehistence is a complication of wound healing.
Basically, it's when the wound opens.
There's a rupture of a wound.
And it's most commonly seen after abdominal surgery, where the actual wound can tear open.
And that's called dehiscence.
Hypertrophic scar.
What's a hypertrophic scar?
It is excess production of scar tissue, but it is localized to the wound.
Here's a classic example.
This patient had a scar, or had a wound, but notice that the scar is a little thick and
prominent.
And so this is an example of a hypertrophic scar.
The hypertrophic scar is predominantly made of type 1 collagen.
So there was granulation tissue, which was type 3.
The collagenase plus zinc came in, converted the type 3 collagen to type 1 collagen.
And so this is excess production of type 1 collagen as part of an aberration of normal scarring.
So that's called a hypertrophic scar.
Another example of a problem with wound healing is called a keloid.
And this is very high yield.
It likes to show up on exams.
So keloid is excess production of scar tissue, but it's way out of proportion to the wound.
Way out of proportion to the wound.
And another important feature of a keloid is that it is characterized by type 3 collagen.
There's an excess of type 3 collagen in the keloid.
There's a genetic predisposition.
It's more commonly seen in African Americans.
And the classic location is the earlobe.
So these are some important facts or features of a keloid.
You need to be familiar with these for the purposes of board examinations.
And here is a classic picture.
So this patient, for example, may have undergone a tiny little ear piercing.
And in response to that tiny ear piercing, this large tumor-like mass developed.
And so this is the keloid.
And so, again, classic features.
The keloid predominantly contains type 3 collagen.
You need to know that.
It's way out of proportion to the wound.
A tiny little ear piercing.
It results in a large tumor-like mass.
And then, important to also know about keloids, genetic predisposition in African Americans.
And also classically seen in the earlobe.
So those are some of the high yields concerning the keloid.
So that really ties up the Chapter 2 discussion of inflammation.
So a lot to be familiar with.
But, again, not too hard if you understand some of the basic principles.
So, let's see.